Finding Aid for Henry Wirt Newkirk Papers, 1862-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Wirt Newkirk Papers 1862-1931
Newkirk, Henry Wirt, 1854-1946.
0.5 linear ft.
851978 Aa 2
Member of the Michigan State Legislature. Personal papers include correspondence, speeches and writings, a scrapbook, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Birkett Newkirk (donor no. 2191 ) and came to the library in 1946.
The collection is open to research.
Attorney from Luther and Dexter, Michigan, Republican state representative from Osceola and Lake Counties, 1893-1894, Dexter businessman, Washtenaw County probate judge, state representative from Washtenaw County, 1907-1910 and 1917-1918, and mayor of Ann Arbor, 1931-1933.
The collection has been arranged into a single series of Personal papers. Included are correspondence; two volumes of speeches and other writings concerning prohibition, woman suffrage, and other political and patriotic subjects; scrapbook, family materials, and miscellanea. Within the correspondence, there are collected letters of Michigan Senator Charles E. Townsend, 1913-1914, and a letter from Benjamin R. Tillman concerning smoking in the U.S. Senate. Other correspondents include J. G. Cannon, Secretary of State William J. Bryan, Booker T. Washington, James B. Angell, Frank Knox, Harry B. Hutchins, Charles E. Townsend, and Earl C. Michener.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Dexter (Mich.); Judges--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Lake County (Mich.); Lawyers--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Luther (Mich.); Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Newkirk, Henry Wirt, 1854-1946.; Osceola County (Mich.); Prohibition--Michigan.; Republican Party (Mich.); Smoking.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Women--Suffrage--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Business enterprises--Michigan--Luther.; Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), b. 1875.; Deckerville (Mich.); Dexter (Mich.)--Mills.; Dexter Union School (Dexter, Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Luther.; Dwellings--Michigan--Portage Lake (Livingston County and Washtenaw County); Lake County (Mich.); Lumber industry.; Luther (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Luther (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Luther (Mich.)--Streets.; Michigan. Legislature (37th: 1893); Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Mills--Michigan--Dexter.; Mills--Michigan--Petoskey.; Mills--Michigan--Portage Lake (Livingston County and Washtenaw County); Newkirk, Henry Wirt, 1854-1946.; Newspaper industry.; Photography.; Petoskey (Mich.); Petoskey (Mich.)--Mills.; Portage Lake (Livingston County and Washtenaw County, Mich.)--Dwellings.; Portage Lake (Livingston County and Washtenaw County, Mich.)--Mills.; Portage Lake (Livingston County and Washtenaw County, Mich.)
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Cannon, Joseph Gurney, 1836-1926.; Cutcheon, Byron M., 1836-1908.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944.; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Tillman, Benjamin R. (Benjamin Ryan), 1847-1918.; Townsend, Charles Elroy, 1856-1924.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Williams, John Sharp, 1854-1932.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Silhouettes.
- Personal papers
  - Biographical and genealogical material (Box 1)
  - Family letters, 1862-1893 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1893-1897 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
    - 1910-1931 (Box 1)
  - Collected letters of Charles E. Townsend, 1913-1914 (Box 1)
  - Letter from A.B. to Col. Preston concerning court case involving a slave in Mississippi prior to the Civil War, 1874 (Box 1)
  - Copy of Kentucky newspaper published by Newkirk, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Military commission issued to Henry Johnson and signed by Dewitt Clinton, April 24, 1818 (Box 1)
  - Ledger (purpose unclear) (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings, memorabilia, and letters, ca. 1893-1913 (Box 1)
  - Republican Party miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Certificates of appointment and election, invitations, programs, etc. (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea; include clippings, etc. (Box 1)
  - Speeches and other writings, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 3 envelopes (Box 1)
    The photographs file includes prints of mills in Portage Lake, Dexter, and Petoskey, Michigan; photographs of dwellings and businesses in Luther, Michigan; group and individual portraits of Michigan legislators and other photographs relating to Newkirk's political career.